Number of pages: 16

================================================================================

--- Page 1 ---

Game Design by Tory Niemann
Art by Mark Maxwell ? Graphic Design by Karim Chakroun  ? 2011 Clever Mojo Games


================================================================================

--- Page 2 ---

Alien Frontiers Overview 
Alien Frontiers is a game of resource management 
and planetary development for two to four players. During 
the game you will exploit orbital facilities and alien 
technology, building colony domes in strategic locations to 
control the newly discovered world. 
The game board shows the planet, its moon, the 
stations in orbit around the planet, and the solar system?s 
star. The dice you are given at the start of the game 
represent the spaceships in your fleet. You will assign these 
ships to the orbital facilities in order to earn resources, 
expand your fleet, and colonize the planet.
As the game proceeds, you will land your colonies on 
the planet to control its territories. Each territory carries a 
particular benefit and, if you control a territory, you are 
able to use that influence to your advantage.
The planet was once the home of an alien race and 
they left behind a wondrous artifact in orbit. Using your 
fleet to explore the artifact, you will discover amazing 
alien technologies that you can use to advance your cause.
Winning the game will require careful consideration 
as you assign your fleet, integrate the alien technology 
and territory bonuses into your expansion plans, and 
block your opponents from building colonies of their own.  
Do you have what it takes to colonize a new world?Credits
Game Design : Tory Niemann  
Art : Mark Maxwell  
Graphic Design : Karim Chakroun  
Publisher : Clever Mojo Games  
Playtesters :
Shawn Anderson
Randall BartZack BarthZach CarterDustin ChapmanLaurel EddyHunter ElenbaasKay GordonLarry GordonShane HarrisDarlene HartfordAndrew HaynesTom HillmanJennifer HodgdonSarah HowardLorraine JohnsonNoah KolmanSandra KuallsMark LoenAlice MacKenzie David MacKenzieFred MacKenzieJohn MacKenzieEric MaxeyScot McConnachieChristopher MillsMichelle Sparr MillsKirk MonsenChuck MonsonDonna MorinaPeter MumfordDan NassetDavin NathansonMark NielsenMelissa NiemannChristopher PaulSpencer PerkinsEvan PongrssJohn ReiherHoward SaccolitiAndrew ShapiraMike SnivelyJT TraubDavid UdellMichael UdellRobert UdellSteve Ward
And The UOPX 
Lunchtime Gamers
Important Notes
Throughout these rules the words ?ship? or ?ships? are 
synonymous with the words ?die? or ?dice?. They are used 
interchangeably.
Objective
Gaining more influence over the Alien Frontier (measured 
in Victory Points) than your opponents by building colonies 
and controlling territories.
2

================================================================================

--- Page 3 ---

24 Ships in Four Colors
22 Alien Tech Cards 8 Territory 
Counters3 Field Generator 
Counters20 Gray ore Tokens 30 Orange fuel Tokens 36 Colony Tokens in Four Colors 1 Relic Ship
1 Game BoardComponents
1 Victory Point
Scoreboard
3

================================================================================

--- Page 4 ---

4

================================================================================

--- Page 5 ---

4 Player Setup
Unfold the game board and place it on the table where it 
is accessible to all players. Place the scoring track board 
in a convenient location and place an unused colony 
token of each color on the 0 line. Assign one player to 
keep track of the victory points throughout the game.
Place the clear die in the square on the Burroughs Desert 
territory. This is the Relic Ship. Place each territory card 
face-up on the matching territory on the board. 
Place the orange fuel tokens on the table near the solar 
converter. This is the fuel stock. 
Place the gray ore tokens on the table near the lunar 
mine. This is the ore stock.
Shuffle the alien tech cards and deal three cards face-
up on the table near the Alien Artifact. This is your alien 
tech stock. Deal one alien tech card face-up to each 
player. The remaining alien tech cards form a draw pile 
that will be used at various times during the game. A 
discard pile will form as the game progresses.
Place the three field generator counters on the table to 
the left of the board.
Each player chooses a color then takes three ships 
(dice) of that color and places them on the Shipyard 
image near the words ?Maintenance Bay?. Place the 
remaining three ships of each color on the table near 
the Shipyard. This is the ship stock.
Each player takes six colony tokens of the color that 
matches their ships. Return the unused colony tokens 
to the game box, they will not be needed.
Choose player one by rolling for high number. Counting 
clockwise from player one, player two receives one fuel, 
player three receives one ore, and player four receives 
one fuel and one ore. This allotment compensates 
for turn-order disparities. Players do not receive this 
allotment each turn.3 Player Variant 
Each player takes seven colony tokens. 
Take the ships of the unclaimed color, turn them all 
so that the 1 faces are on top, and use them to cover 
docking ports marked with three dots. 
 ?One ship at the Solar Converter, 
 ?One ship at the Lunar Mine, 
 ?Two ships at the Orbital Market,
 ?Two ships at the Shipyard. 
These ships will stay in place throughout the game and 
may not be moved, removed, or changed.
At the beginning of the game, player two receives one 
fuel token and player three receives one ore token.
2 Player Variant 
Each player takes eight colony tokens. 
Take the ships of the unclaimed colors, turn them all 
so that the 1 faces are on top, and use them to cover all 
docking ports marked with dots.
 ?One ship at the Solar Converter, 
 ?Two ships at the Lunar Mine, 
 ?Two ships at the Orbital Market, 
 ?Three ships at the Colony Constructor, 
 ?Four ships at the Shipyard. 
These ships will stay in place throughout the game and 
may not be moved, removed, or changed. 
At the beginning of the game, player two receives one 
fuel token.
Long-Game Variant 
Once you become skilled at Alien Frontiers you may 
wish to play longer games. To do this in the 4-player 
and 3-player scenarios, each player starts with all eight 
of their colony tokens.
5

================================================================================

--- Page 6 ---

Game Play
Play begins with player one and moves clockwise. 
Each player performs the following tasks on their 
turn: 
Gather and Roll Your Fleet  
Gather all of your ships from the board and roll 
them.
Use Alien Tech Cards and Assign 
Your Fleet  
Do these tasks in any order you like. You may 
choose to use all, some, or none of your alien 
tech cards but you must dock all of your ships 
at orbital facilities on your turn if possible. If 
you cannot legally dock one or more of your 
ships at any orbital facility, place them on the 
Maintenance Bay.
You may use an orbital facility by allocating your 
ships to its docking ports. A facility can only be 
used if it has sufficient unused docking ports, 
you have ships of the required values, and you 
can immediately  pay any applicable cost. See the 
section on orbital facilities for the requirements 
and costs for each facility.
Example?:
The terraforming station requires a value 6 ship 
and costs one fuel and one ore. Therefore, you 
may not use the terraforming station if you do 
not have any sixes, if the single docking port 
is already occupied, or if you do not have the 
required fuel and ore. 
You gain the benefits of an orbital facility, 
territory control, or alien tech immediately 
unless noted otherwise. Costs to use orbital facilities and alien tech cards 
are paid to the stocks.
You may use your alien tech cards at any time 
during your turn. Most cards have a power you 
pay fuel to use and a power you must discard the 
card to use. Each alien tech card may be used 
only once per turn. You may only use one discard 
power from your alien tech cards each turn. 
See the rules section on alien tech cards for the 
powers and costs of each card.
If you place a colony during your turn you 
earn a victory point and adjust the score track 
immediately. If colony placement results in 
your having more colonies on the territory 
than any other player, you ?control? that 
territory.  You take its counter, gain an extra 
victory point, and may use the territory?s bonus. 
If you no longer have more colonies on the 
territory than any other player, you lose control 
of the territory. You immediately return the 
territory card to the planet, lose a victory point, 
and can no longer use the territory?s bonus. See 
the rules section on territory bonuses for details.
The presence of certain field generators may 
award an extra victory point or limit your ability 
to use territory bonuses and place colonies. See 
the rules section on field generators for details.
End of Turn 
When you have docked all your ships on the 
board and used any alien tech cards that you 
wanted to use, your turn is over. Leave your ships 
as you have docked them until your next turn.
If you have more than eight total resource tokens 
at the end of your turn you must 
return your choice of excess 
tokens to the appropriate 
resource stocks.End of Game  
and Scoring
Scoring is not cumulative. It is a snapshot of the 
current board and hand situation at any single 
point in time. Use the scoreboard to track the 
current standings throughout the game. Your 
score will fluctuate up and down as the game 
progresses, and each time circumstances change 
the scoreboard should be updated.
You score 1 victory point for...
 ?Each of your colony tokens on a 
territory
 ?Each territory you control
 ?Having the Alien City card
 ?Having the Alien Monument card
 ?Controlling the territory with the 
Positron Field
The game ends as soon as one player places their 
last colony on a territory. Players tally up their 
victory points to verify the standings on the 
scoreboard, and the player with the most victory 
points wins.
If there is a tie, the tied players compare their 
number of alien tech cards to determine the 
winner. Persistent ties can be resolved by 
comparing ore tokens then fuel tokens. Still tied? 
Play again!
6

================================================================================

--- Page 7 ---

Orbital Facilities
Surrounding the planet are the orbital facilities you 
will use to earn resources, expand your fleet, and land 
colonies. You may not dock ships at an orbital facility 
unless docking ports are available and you can meet 
both the ship and cost requirements. 
Alien Artifact  
Each ship you dock at the Alien Artifact may be of any 
value and allows you to discard the alien tech cards on 
display and lay out three new cards from the deck. This is 
called ?cycling? and it is optional. 
To claim one of the alien tech cards on display you need to 
have docked ships with a total value of 8 or more. When you 
claim an alien tech card the count is reset to zero, so, to claim 
another card you need to dock new ships totaling 8 or more. 
Replace the claimed card with one from the draw pile. You 
may not claim an alien tech card you already have. There are 
enough docking ports to accommodate four ships at a time. 
Example?1?:
There is a Polarity Device card on display and you 
want it, so you dock a 2 and a 6 at the Alien Artifact 
and take the card. 
Example?2?:
You dock a 3 at the Alien Artifact and cycle the alien 
tech cards. There?s nothing you want so you dock a 
2 and cycle the cards again. You still have not found 
what you want so you dock a 4 and cycle the cards 
a third time. The Plasma Cannon is now on display. 
Since your docked ships total 8 or more (3+2+4=9) 
you take the Plasma Cannon.
Example?3?:
After completing the moves in example 2 there is one dock open at the Alien Artifact. You could dock a 
fourth ship there and cycle the cards again but you 
could not claim a second alien tech card because the 
?8 or more? requirement is a separate total for each 
card you claim.
Colonist Hub  
The Colonist Hub has four ?advancement tracks? so 
that four players can use it simultaneously to ready 
colonies for territory placement. Each track contains 
three docking ports and seven advancement circles. A 
player may use only one advancement track at a time.
If you do not have a colony at the Colonist Hub then 
the first ship docked here requires you to place one of 
your unplaced colonies on the first advancement circle. 
Each additional ship you dock here, either on this turn 
or on subsequent turns, must be placed on this same 
track until that colony is launched. Each ship docked 
advances the colony one circle. When the colony reaches 
the seventh advancement circle you may launch it at 
your convenience by paying one fuel and one ore. You 
may not begin work on another colony at the Colonist 
Hub until the one already on the advancement track 
has been launched. Once the colony has been placed on 
a territory you may start advancing a new colony with 
the next ship you dock at the Colonist Hub. 
If you earn more advances than are needed to move 
your colony to the seventh circle (see Asimov Crater 
below) and launch the colony immediately, you may 
use the excess advances to begin work on a new colony.  
 
Your final colony is not locked into the Colonist Hub. 
If your last colony is on the Colonist Hub and your 
roll gives you the opportunity to use the Terraforming 
Station or the Colony Constructor, you may remove the 
colony from the Colonist Hub and place it on a territory 
via the rules for those other facilities.
Colonist?Hub
Colony?Constructor
Alien?Artifact
7

================================================================================

--- Page 8 ---

Colony Constructor 
You must dock three ships of equal value and pay three ore 
to use the Colony Constructor. There are enough docking 
ports for two sets of triples to be docked simultaneously. 
Using the Colony Constructor allows you to land one of 
your unplaced colonies on a territory immediately.
Lunar Mine  
Each new ship docked at the Lunar Mine must be equal 
to or greater than the highest value ship currently 
docked here. There are enough docking ports to 
accommodate five ships at any one time. You gain one 
ore for each ship you dock here. 
Example?:?
At the beginning of your turn there is a 1 and a 4 docked 
at the Lunar Mine. You roll a 3, 4, and 6. You cannot dock 
the 3 at the Lunar Mine because it is less than the 4 already 
docked there, but you can dock both your 4 and your 6. You 
earn two ore for docking both ships at the Lunar Mine. The 
Lunar Mine now has only one docking port free and the 
next player that wants to use it will need a 6. 
Maintenance Bay  
If you cannot dock a ship legally during your turn, 
place it here. Maintenance Bay gives the player no 
benefit. Any ships purchased through the Shipyard 
or Burroughs Desert are placed here until the 
player?s next turn. A ship on the Maintenance Bay 
cannot be moved with an alien tech card. Ships 
removed from facilities with the Plasma Cannon or 
bumped from the Raiders? Outpost are placed at the Maintenance Bay until their player?s next turn. 
Orbital Market 
You must dock two ships of equal value to use the 
Orbital Market. There are enough docking ports to 
accommodate two pairs of ships at any one time. While 
docked at the Orbital Market you may pay fuel equal to 
the value of one of your docked ships to receive one ore. 
You may trade as many times as you wish on your turn.
Example?:?
You dock a pair of 3s at the Orbital Market. On this turn 
you may pay three fuel to receive one ore. If you have six 
fuel you may do the trade twice. If you acquire three more 
fuel during your turn you may do the trade again.
Raiders? Outpost 
You must dock a set of three sequentially numbered ships 
to use the Raiders? Outpost. There are docking ports for 
one set of three ships. If the Raiders? Outpost is occupied, 
either by your own ships or by the ships of another player, 
you may dock a higher-value sequence here and move the 
original ships to the Maintenance Bay. 
While docked at the Raiders? Outpost you may steal a total 
of four resources from any mix of players or one alien tech 
card of your choice from one player. If you steal an alien 
tech card that you already have, the stolen card is discarded 
immediately and you gain no benefit from doing so. 
Example? ?1:
If a 1-2-3 is docked at the Raiders? Outpost and 
the next player rolls a 2-3-4 then that player may 
remove the 1-2-3 and dock their 2-3-4 at the facility 
to conduct their own raid. If another player rolls a 
3-4-5 or a 4-5-6 then they may remove the 2-3-4 and 
Lunar?Mine
Orbital?Market
Raiders??Outpost
8

================================================================================

--- Page 9 ---

dock their own sequence and conduct their own raid. 
Example? ?2:?
A 3-4-5 are docked at the Raiders? Outpost. You 
use the Plasma Cannon to send the 5 back to the 
Maintenance Bay, leaving a 3 and 4 on the Raiders? 
Outpost. To dock a higher-value sequence at the 
Raiders? Outpost you must use a run of three ships 
that totals more than the sum of the ships currently 
docked there. The remaining ships total 7 so you may 
not dock a 1-2-3 since they only total 6. However, you 
may dock a 2-3-4 (total 9), a 3-4-5 (total 12) or a 
4-5-6 (total 15) to use the Raiders? Outpost.  
Shipyard  
You must dock two ships of equal value to use 
the Shipyard. There are enough docking ports to 
accommodate three pairs of ships at any one time. 
Each pair of docked ships, along with the payment of 
the appropriate fuel and ore, earns one new ship from 
the ship stock. 
 ?4th ship : pay one fuel and one ore. 
 ?5th ship : pay two fuel and two ore. 
 ?6th ship : pay three fuel and three ore. 
Take a ship of your color from the ship stock and place 
it in the Maintenance Bay. Claim it at the start of your 
next turn when you gather your fleet. If there are no 
ships of your color in the ship stock on your turn then 
you may not use the Shipyard. Because it is possible to 
lose ships while playing, you may build your 4th, 5th, 
or 6th ship more than once during the game.Solar Converter 
You may dock ships of any value at the Solar Converter. 
There are enough docking ports to accommodate eight 
ships. You gain fuel equal to one half the value of each 
ship you dock here. Round up for each ship. 
Example?:?
If you dock a 3 and a 4 at the solar converter you will 
receive two fuel for the 3 and two fuel for the 4.
Terraforming Station 
You must dock one ship with a value of 6 and pay one 
fuel and one ore to use the Terraforming Station. There 
is only one docking port available at this facility. Using 
the Terraforming Station allows you to land one of 
your unplaced colonies on a territory immediately. The 
ship docked at the Terraforming Station is completely 
consumed by the colony creation process and is returned 
to the ship stock at the beginning of your next turn. A 
ship forfeited in this manner may be rebuilt using the 
Shipyard only after it has returned to the ship stock. 
You cannot use the Terraforming Station if doing so 
would reduce your fleet to fewer than three ships of 
your color. 
A ship docked at the Terraforming Station may be 
removed by the Plasma Cannon card but may not be 
moved to another orbital facility.
Shipyard
Solar?Converter
Terraforming?Station
9

================================================================================

--- Page 10 ---

Territory Bonuses
Each territory grants its controlling player a 
bonus over some aspect of the game. A player 
controls a territory if they have more colonies on 
that territory than any other single player. The 
controlling player takes the territory counter.
Example:
Red has two colonies on Lem Badlands and 
Green, Yellow, and Blue each have one colony 
on Lem Badlands. Red has the most colonies 
on the territory so Red controls Lem Badlands.
A territory is not controlled by any player if two 
or more players are tied for the most colonies on 
a territory.  No player earns the bonus for such 
a territory. The counter for a territory that is not 
controlled remains on the territory.
Example:
Red and Yellow each have two colonies on Lem 
Badlands and Green and Blue each have one 
colony on Lem Badlands. Red and Yellow are 
tied for the most colonies on the territory so it is 
not controlled by anyone and no one earns the 
territory?s bonus. 
Asimov Crater  
Advance your colony one extra level each turn 
in which you dock more than one ship at the 
Colonist Hub.
Example:?
Docking two ships at the Colonist Hub would 
ordinarily advance your colony two levels. Since 
you control Asimov Crater, you advance your 
colony three levels. If you dock three ships at the 
Colonist Hub you would advance four levels.Bradbury Plateau 
Pay one less ore than usual when you use the 
Colony Constructor.
Example:?
You dock a set of three 5s at the Colony 
Constructor to build a colony. Ordinarily 
you would be required to pay three ore to 
activate the facility. However, since you control 
Bradbury Plateau, you pay only two ore.
Burroughs Desert 
Purchase the Relic Ship for 1 fuel and 1 ore. Place 
the ship on the Maintenance Bay and gather 
it with the rest of your fleet on your next turn. 
Return the ship to Burroughs Desert immediately 
if you lose control of this territory. The Relic Ship 
behaves exactly as any other ship in your fleet 
except that it has no color and any time the ship 
would be returned to the ship stock it is returned 
to Burroughs Desert instead.
See Terraforming Station and the discard power 
of a Plasma Cannon card for details. The player 
controlling Burroughs Desert may repurchase 
the Relic Ship on their turn.
Example?1:?
You control Burroughs Desert with one colony 
and are using the Relic Ship. The next player 
builds a new colony and places it on Burroughs 
Desert. Now you both have one colony on 
Burroughs Desert so neither of you control the 
territory. You return the territory card and the 
Relic Ship to Burroughs Desert immediately.Example?2:?
Your Relic Ship is docked at the Lunar Mine. 
Another player discards a Stasis Beam and 
places the Isolation Field on Burroughs Desert. 
You must return the Relic Ship to the territory 
immediately and may not repurchase it until the 
Isolation Field is moved off Burroughs Desert.
Example?3:?
Your Relic Ship has a 6 showing and you dock 
it at the Terraforming Station to build a colony. 
At the start of your next turn the Relic Ship 
returns to Burroughs Desert instead of the ship 
stock and you may repurchase it on that same 
turn.
Heinlein Plains 
Your trading ratio is always 1 fuel for 1 ore when 
using the Orbital Market.
Example:?
You roll double 3s and dock them at the Orbital 
Market. Ordinarily any trades you make on this 
turn would be at a three fuel for one ore ratio. 
However, since you control Heinlein Plains you 
always trade at a one fuel for one ore ratio 
regardless of your docked ship values.
10

================================================================================

--- Page 11 ---

Herbert Valley 
Pay 1 less fuel and ore than usual for each ship 
you build at the Shipyard.
Example:?
You dock a pair of ships at the Shipyard to build 
your 5th ship. Ordinarily you would also pay 
2 fuel and 2 ore. However, since you control 
Herbert Valley you pay only 1 fuel and 1 ore. 
If it had been your 4th ship, the bonus from 
Herbert Valley would have allowed you to pay 
nothing at all.
Lem Badlands 
Gain 1 additional fuel for each ship you dock at 
the Solar Converter.
Example:?
You dock a 3 and 4 at the Solar Converter and 
receive the usual 4 fuel. Because you control 
Lem Badlands, you gain two extra fuel.
Pohl Foothills  
Pay one less fuel than normal for each alien tech 
card you use.
Example?1:?
You have a Booster Pod card which allows you 
to add 1 to the value of an unplaced ship at a 
cost of 1 fuel. Since you control Pohl Foothills, 
you pay nothing for this manipulation.Example?2:?
You have a Plasma Cannon card which allows 
you to remove opponents? ships from an orbital 
facility at a cost of one fuel per ship. You choose 
to remove three ships from the Lunar Mine. 
Since you control Pohl Foothills you only pay 2 
fuel for this action.
Van Vogt Mountains  
The first ship you dock at the Lunar Mine each 
turn may be any value.
Example:?
You rolled a 1, 2, 4, and 5 and the highest value 
ship at the Lunar Mine is currently a 5. Since 
you control Van Vogt Mountains, the first ship 
you dock at the Lunar Mine may be the 1, 2, or 
4. If you want to receive a second ore you can 
also dock the 5 at the Lunar Mine.
11

================================================================================

--- Page 12 ---

Field Generators
The three field generators alter the rules within 
the territory where they are located and, where 
there is a conflict, take precedence over alien 
tech card effects.
Isolation Field 
The Isolation Field nullifies a territory?s bonus. 
The first player to discard a Stasis Beam card will 
place the Isolation Field counter on a territory of 
their choice. Any subsequent player who discards 
a Stasis Beam card will move the counter to 
another territory.
Example:?
If the Isolation Field is placed on Pohl Foothills, 
the player who controls that territory does not 
receive the ?pay one less fuel than normal on 
each alien tech card you use? bonus and the 
bonus is not available to a player using a Data 
Crystal card. Positron Field  
The Positron Field awards one victory point to 
the player controlling the territory where it is 
located. The first player to discard a Data Crystal 
card will place the Positron Field counter on a 
territory of their choice. Any subsequent player 
who discards a Data Crystal card will move the 
counter to another territory. 
Example:?
If the Positron Field is located on Herbert Valley 
and the green player controls Herbert Valley, 
then the green player receives one additional 
victory point. Repulsor Field 
The Repulsor Field prevents colonies from 
being added to or removed from the territory 
on which it is located. The Repulsor Field does 
not prevent its own movement or removal, nor 
does it prevent the movement or removal of any 
other field generator that is also on that territory. 
The first player to discard a Gravity Manipulator 
card will place the Repulsor Field counter on a 
territory of their choice. Any subsequent player 
who discards a Gravity Manipulator card will 
move the counter to another territory.
Example:?
If the Repulsor Field is on Asimov Crater then 
no new colonies may be added on that territory 
and the colonies already there cannot be 
swapped or removed by discarding a Polarity 
Device or Orbital Teleporter card. 
12

================================================================================

--- Page 13 ---

Alien Tech Cards
The alien tech cards allow you to bend the basic game 
rules. Most alien tech cards may be used immediately 
after you acquire them. Alien tech cards that require a 
fuel payment can only be used once per turn. You may 
only discard an alien tech card you have not already 
used on your current turn and then only one discard 
per turn. 
Your alien tech cards are placed on the table face-up 
where all players can see them.
You may only possess one copy of each alien tech card. 
If a card allows you to change a ship?s value then the 
value may never be lower than 1 or higher than 6.
If the alien tech draw deck is exhausted, reshuffle the 
discards to create a new draw deck.
Alien City and Alien Monument  
Each of these cards is worth one victory point. There is 
one Alien City card and one Alien Monument card in 
the alien tech deck and a single player may possess both 
cards simultaneously. There is no fuel cost associated 
with these cards and they do not have discard powers.
Booster Pod  
Each turn you may pay one fuel to increase the value 
of one of your unplaced ships by one point. You may 
discard a Booster Pod to remove any single field 
generator from the game board. A field generator 
removed in this manner may be rebuilt in the normal 
manner at a later time.
Example:?
You roll a 1, 3, and 4. You pay one fuel and use the 
Booster Pod?s power to raise the 3 to a 4 so that you 
can use the pair of 4s at the Shipyard.Data Crystal  
Each turn you may pay one fuel per colony on a territory 
to use that territory?s bonus exactly as if you controlled 
the territory. If a territory has no colonies on it then you 
cannot use its bonus. If the territory has the Isolation 
Field on it then you cannot use its bonus. Burroughs 
Desert is exempt from the Data Crystal?s power because 
its bonus plays out over more than a single turn. You 
may discard a Data Crystal to place the Positron Field 
on a territory or, if the Positron Field is already on a 
territory, move it to another territory.
Example:?
You roll a 1, 6, and 6. You have a lot of fuel and you 
need to convert it to ore, but the pair of 6s gives you a 
very poor trading ratio at the Orbital Market. Heinlein 
Plains has one green colony and one red colony on 
it, so you pay two fuel and use your Data Crystal to 
borrow the Heinlein Plains bonus. You now receive a 
1:1 trade ratio at the Orbital Market, no matter what 
value pair you dock there. 
Gravity Manipulator 
Each turn you may pay two fuel to decrease the value 
of one unplaced ship by one point and increase the 
value of another unplaced ship by one point. You may 
discard a Gravity Manipulator to place the Repulsor 
Field on a territory or, if the Repulsor Field is already 
on a territory, move it to another territory.
Example?:?
You roll a 1, 2, and 5. You pay two fuel and use the 
Gravity Manipulator to move one point from the 2 to 
the 5 making those two ships into a 1 and a 6.
Alien?City
Alien?Monument
Booster?Pod
Data?Crystal
13

================================================================================

--- Page 14 ---

Holographic Decoy 
There is no fuel cost associated with this card and it 
does not have a discard power. While you possess the 
Holographic Decoy a player may not use the Raiders? 
Outpost to steal resources from you. If the raiding 
player wishes to steal an alien tech card from you then 
they may only take your Holographic Decoy. If the 
raiding player already has a Holographic Decoy then 
the stolen card is discarded.
Example?:?
The red player places three sequentially numbered 
ships on the Raiders? Outpost. They would like to 
steal four ore from you but because you have the 
Holographic Decoy card your ore is safe. However, 
the red player decides to take your Holographic Decoy 
card instead.
Orbital Teleporter 
Each turn you may pay two fuel to move one of your 
docked ships from one orbital facility to a different orbital 
facility. You may only move one of your ships with the 
Orbital Teleporter but the moved ship may be used at 
the new facility in conjunction with other as yet unplaced 
ships from your fleet. You may not reuse the ship at the 
same facility from which it was removed. You may not 
change the value of the ship as it moves from one facility to 
the other. You may not use the Orbital Teleporter to move 
a ship off of the Terraforming Station or the Maintenance 
Bay. You may discard the Orbital Teleporter to move any 
single colony from one territory to another territory. See 
Repulsor Field above for exceptions.
Example?1?:?
You roll a 2, 5, and 6. You dock the 6 at the Lunar 
Mine and receive one ore. You then pay two fuel and 
use your Orbital Teleporter to move the 6 to the Alien 
Artifact. Next you dock the 2 at the Alien Artifact to 
bring the ship total to 8 and claim an alien tech card.
Example?2?:?
You are the blue player. You and the red player 
both have a colony on Lem Badlands so neither of you control it. You have one colony on Van Vogt 
Mountains but green has two colonies there so you 
are not likely to gain control of it any time soon. You 
discard your Orbital Teleporter card and move your 
colony from Van Vogt Mountains to Lem Badlands to 
gain control of that territory, claim the territory card, 
and receive the extra victory point.
Plasma Cannon  
Each turn you may pay one fuel per ship to remove other 
players? ships from one orbital facility. The removed 
ships are placed on the Maintenance Bay (see example 2 
below for an exception to this rule). The Plasma Cannon 
may only remove ships from a single orbital facility and 
you may not use the Plasma Cannon on your own ships. 
You may discard a Plasma Cannon to return one ship 
belonging to another player to the ship stock. The target 
player must not be left with fewer than three ships of 
their color for their next turn. The Relic Ship does not 
count toward this tally. A ship removed in this manner 
may be regained via the Shipyard.
Example?1?:?
You are the blue player and roll a 2, 2, and 4. You want to 
use the pair of 2s at the Shipyard but all of the docks are 
full. You pay 2 fuel and use your Plasma Cannon to move 
two red ships from the Shipyard to the Maintenance Bay 
then dock your own ships at the Shipyard.
Example?2?:
You are the blue player and the red player has a ship 
on the Terraforming Station. You pay one fuel and 
use your Plasma Cannon to move the red ship off the 
Terraforming Station. Ordinarily a ship removed by the 
Plasma Cannon would go to the Maintenance Bay, but a 
ship on the Terraforming Station is forfeit on the player?s 
next turn so you return it to the ship stock instead.
Example?3?:
You are the blue player and the yellow player has six 
ships on the board. You discard your Plasma Cannon 
to remove the yellow 6 from the Lunar Mine and 
return it to the ship stock.
Gravity?Manipulator
Holographic?Decoy
Orbital?Teleporter
Plasma?Cannon
14

================================================================================

--- Page 15 ---

Example?4?:
Red has four ships on the board: one at the Lunar Mine, 
two at the Alien Artifact, and one at the Terraforming 
Station. You want to discard your Plasma Cannon to 
remove the ship on the Lunar Mine but you cannot. 
Doing so would leave Red with three ships now, but on 
Red?s next turn the ship on the Terraforming Station 
would be forfeited and Red would only have two ships 
for the next turn.
Polarity Device 
Each turn you may pay one fuel to flip one of your 
unplaced ships to its opposite face. You may discard 
a Polarity Device to swap the locations of any two 
colonies on any two territories. See Repulsor Field for 
exceptions.
Example?1?:
You roll a 1, 2, and 5. You pay one fuel and use the 
Polarity Device to flip the 1 to a 6.
Example?2?:
Herbert Valley has two yellow colonies on it and Lem 
Badlands has two red colonies on it. You discard the 
Polarity Device and swap one colony from each of 
those territories. Both territories now have one yellow 
colony and one red colony so neither red nor yellow 
control those two territories.
Resource Cache  
You receive free resources each turn for as long as you 
possess the Resource Cache. Count the odd and even 
value ships after you roll your fleet but before you use 
any alien tech cards. 
 ?If you have more odd ships,  
you receive one ore. 
 ?If you have more even ships,  
you receive one fuel. 
 ?If you have an equal number of odd and even 
ships you receive one fuel and one ore and you 
must immediately discard the Resource Cache. Unlike every other alien tech card, the Resource Cache 
cannot be used on the turn you acquire it. 
The Resource Cache card is only discarded if you roll 
equal numbers of odd and even valued ships.
Example?:?
You dock a 3 and a 6 at the Alien Artifact and claim 
a Resource Cache card. You do not gain any benefit 
from the card until your next turn when you gather 
and roll your fleet.
Stasis Beam 
Each turn you may pay one fuel to decrease the value 
of one of your unplaced ships by one point. You may 
discard a Stasis Beam to place the Isolation Field on 
a territory or, if the Isolation Field is already on a 
territory, move it to another territory.
Example?:
You roll a 1, 2 and 5. You pay one fuel and use the 
Stasis Beam?s power to decrease the 2 to a 1 so that 
you can use the pair of 1s to get a favorable trading 
ratio at the Orbital Market.
Temporal Warper 
Each turn you may pay one fuel to re-roll as many of 
your unplaced ships as you like. You may discard a 
Temporal Warper to claim one alien tech card of your 
choice from the discard pile. You may look through the 
discard pile before discarding your Temporal Warper 
card.
Example?1?:
You roll a 1, 2, and 5. You use the Temporal Warper 
to re-roll the 1 and 2, hoping to get some higher 
numbers. 
Example?2?:?
You review the alien tech discard pile and see an Alien 
City card. You discard your Temporal Warper and 
take the Alien City card.
Polarity?Device
Resource?Cache
Stasis?Beam
Temporal?Warper
15

================================================================================

--- Page 16 ---

Quick Play Reference
Objective
Have the most victory points by the end of the game 
through colony placement, territory control, and 
possession of certain alien tech cards.
Turn Flow
Each player performs all of these tasks on their 
turn.
 ?Gather your ships and roll them.
 ?Dock all of your ships to your choice of 
orbital facilities for which you qualify 
and gain benefits immediately.
 ?Use alien tech cards as appropriate at any 
time during your turn. Alien tech cards 
that require a fuel payment can only be 
used once per turn. You may only discard 
an alien tech card you have not already 
used on your current turn and then only 
one discard per turn.
 ?Once all ships have been docked and 
alien tech used, discard down to eight 
resources.
 ?Turn passes to next player.
Game End and Scoring
The game ends immediately when any player lands 
their final unplaced colony on a territory.
Score:
 ?1 VP per colony on a territory
 ?1 VP per territory you control
 ?1 VP for possession of the Alien City card
 ?1 VP for possession of the Alien 
Monument card
 ?1 VP for controlling the territory with the 
Positron Field
Ties are broken by number of alien tech cards. 
Persistent ties are broken by number of ore tokens, 
then by number of fuel tokens.Alien Artifact  
Each ship you dock allows you to cycle the alien tech 
cards. You may claim one card when your docked 
ships total 8 or more. Claiming a second card 
requires you to dock a new set of ships totaling 8 
or more.
Colonist Hub  
Dock ships of any value.  If you do not have a colony 
on the track, place one with your first ship.  Move 
your colony forward one space per ship docked.  If 
your colony is on the final space on the track, pay 
1 fuel and 1 ore to place the colony. Use only one 
track at a time.
Colony Constructor  
Dock three ships of the same value.  Pay 3 ore to 
place a colony.
Lunar Mine  
Dock ships greater than or equal to highest value on 
the Mine.  Gain 1 ore per ship.
Maintenance Bay  
If you cannot dock a ship legally during your turn, 
place it here. Maintenance Bay gives you no benefit. 
Any ships purchased through the Shipyard or 
Burroughs Desert are placed here until your next 
turn. A ship on the Maintenance Bay cannot be 
moved with an alien tech card. Ships removed from 
facilities with the Plasma Cannon or bumped from 
the Raiders? Outpost are placed at the Maintenance 
Bay until their player?s next turn.Orbital Market  
Dock two ships of the same value.  Trade fuel equal 
to value of one ship for one ore.  Trading may be 
done multiple times. 
Raiders? Outpost  
Dock three sequentially numbered ships. Steal a total 
of four resources or one alien tech card from your 
opponent(s). If the Raiders? Outpost is occupied, 
you may dock a higher-value sequence and move 
the original ships to the Maintenance Bay.
Shipyard  
Dock two ships of the same value.  Pay fuel and ore 
to move one of your ships from ship stock to the 
Maintenance Bay : 1 each for your fourth ship, 2 
each for your fifth, and 3 each for your sixth.
Solar Converter  
Take fuel equal to half the value of each ship you 
dock here. Round up for each ship.
Terraforming Station  
Dock a value 6 ship.  Pay 1 fuel and 1 ore to place a 
colony.  Next turn, the ship returns to the ship stock.Icon Reference

================================================================================
